[♪♪♪]
[TIRES SCREECH]
[CAR DOOR OPENS, CLOSES]
[♪♪♪]
[SPLASH]
[TIRES SCREECH]
[CAR REVS OFF]
[♪♪♪]
[BIRDS CHIRPING]
[WHIRS]
[BUZZING]
[GUNSHOTS]
GRAYSMITH:
Your hands are shaking.
[SIGHS]
Go ahead.
Try again.
Enough humiliation
for one day.
I'm not cut out for this.
Why are you lying to me?
The grades haven't come out yet,
but I saw yours already.
You scored higher than most
in every discipline,
even higher than your superiors
when they were cadets.
My teachers?
Myself included.
We've never had someone like you
at this academy.
Why do I sense
this isn't a compliment?
[BEEPS]
[WHIRS]
I can tell a bad shot
from a deliberate miss-aim.
This shooting exam
is the last thing standing
between you and the field,
and I believe I know
what you're doing.
You're self-sabotaging
your own score.
Why would I do that?
Because you're scared
about what's waiting for you
on the other side.
You've been studying evil
for years,
but you had theory
to protect you.
Once you pass this exam,
you're out there on the field
on your own, and you're scared.
You're just beginning
to realize that you're not ready
to confront what real evil
looks like.
Forensics needs me here.
Murder victims
need you, too.
And how are you gonna help them
from behind a desk?
My place is at the academy.
And train others
for the rest of your life?
[SCOFFS]
No.
I refuse to let talent
like yours go to waste.
All due respect, I gotta go.
You better start
taking a real chance
on yourself
before someone else does.
I'll give you one shot.
This next bullet either lands
you your first case
or discharges you before your
field career has even begun.
Fire accordingly.
[CLICKS GUN]
[GUNSHOT]
[DOORS OPEN]
[ELEVATOR BELL DINGS]
[ELEVATOR DOORS SLIDE OPEN]
Oh, oh, wait.
Uh, 12.
Might wanna try vodka.
It's harder to smell.
[PHONE RINGING IN BACKGROUND]
[♪♪♪]
GRAYSMITH:
See that man right there?
Some would say his political
authority is absolute.
Why am I here?
Yesterday, his two
twin daughters disappeared.
They found a body
a few hours ago
face down in a river,
murdered.
She was 14.
ALAN:
But the other sister
is still missing.
He talked
to the local police,
got it to be
a co-investigation, private.
No outside interference.
When would this start?
GRAYSMITH:
It already has.
But?
But he believes this case
deserves more
of a personal touch.
Is that why he's here?
GRAYSMITH:
Yes.
I know what you're gonna say.
[DROPS FILE]
I read your petition,
and if these really are
your last few months,
who wouldn't wanna spend it
safely behind a desk?
Glad you understand.
I need you to lead this case.
Study the crime scene,
analyze all the clues,
find the kidnapper,
bring back the missing child
before it's too late.
I'm sorry.
I misunderstood.
I thought I was here
for a different offer.
I hope you find the right person
for the job,
somebody with a little less
baggage.
I'll sign
your retirement papers.
You need my signature.
This case is your ticket out.
You take it, and I'll make sure
it's your last.
Erica--
GRAYSMITH: Look, I know
what you're going through.
And trust me, we miss him too,
but a single case
can't be enough
to dismantle an entire career.
He'll be in here any moment,
and what do you want me
to tell him?
They're letting you
send in one man?
GRAYSMITH:
You won't be alone.
There's a woman in the agency.
They're enforcing assistance?
I'm offering assistance.
Whoever she is,
I don't need her.
Her two degrees in forensic
psychology beg to differ.
ALAN:
Erica--
I'll join you there
as soon as I can,
but for now,
there's a train that leaves
in 60 minutes, and I'm intending
for you both to be on it.
So are you in or out?
[DOOR OPENS]
[SIGHS]
Detective, I don't want
my daughter's last memory to be
of a father
who couldn't save her.
I need to know
that I tried everything.
Please.
What would you do?
[TWISTS CAP]
[INDISTINCT CHATTER
IN BACKGROUND]
AMELIA:
You look so different
in pictures.
Says here you've been at it
for 20 years,
10 of them working alone.
Now you've got yourself
a brand-new partner.
We're not partners.
AMELIA:
Yet you haven't spoken
to me since we got here,
no word of warning or advice,
so I can't tell if you're either
too relaxed to have me here
or too worried.
I'm a criminologist,
not a babysitter.
Did I do something to offend?
Graysmith thinks having you here
will solve the case quicker,
maybe prevent me
from making a mess.
Now, I agree
with the second part,
but what she thinks
we have in common,
I don't know that yet.
We've both chosen
to take murder
and make it our business.
You track killers;
I diagnose them.
Same sickness, different angle.
You know nothing about
diagnosing people.
Right heel cap
on your shoe is torn up,
shallow bite marks,
wide spacing.
Large breed of dog, I'd say,
based on the bite.
Maybe you adopted one recently
for companionship
after losing
a friend or a family member.
Do you always carry the photo
or is it a--
a ritual of sorts
before you begin a case?
Happens all the time
after breakups.
People don't get rid
of an old photo,
but they'll fold over the parts
that hurt the most.
They wanna remember the rest.
What was he like?
We haven't even
left the station,
but I can tell already.
Business and feelings,
they don't go well in this
line of work.
Okay?
Okay.
ALAN: Yeah?
You don't have
to worry about me.
I'm here for research,
pure and simple.
ALAN:
Good.
I think the question is,
why would Graysmith give you
this case?
[TRAIN PASSING BY]
[TRAIN HORN BLARES]
AMELIA:
Where do we find him?
ALAN:
I'm hoping he finds us.
AMELIA:
Your suede coat
was a great choice.
You really don't smile,
do you?
Alan Kramer?
[CAMERA SHUTTER CLICKING]
Can I help you?
Hey, hey.
Hold onto the negatives.
ALAN:
You greet all
new arrivals this way?
Only the ones worth
talking about.
Huh.
Alan Kramer?
Yes, sir.
Hank Brewster.
Lieutenant.
It's hard not to recognize
a face like yours, though.
I can hardly believe
you're here.
Right.
This your first time
in Canton, ma'am?
I don't travel much.
Well, I fear you'll be surprised
in all the worst ways.
I don't know how much they told
you before you left, but--
Not much.
We left in a hurry.
All right.
This is Arthur Otto.
He's a senator, philanthropist,
family man.
Most of the buildings
in this town were rescued
through his charity.
Politicians dream
of a reputation like that.
This guy's actually earned it.
AMELIA:
He's financing
an additional investigation?
Yeah, no expense spared.
His campaign's recruited
hundreds of volunteers,
organized search parties,
but after this morning's news--
It's no longer enough.
By the way, I took the
trouble to get you guys set up.
Your case files and bags
are in your rooms.
How far is the police station
from the hotel?
Any closer,
you'd be sleeping in my office.
Now, I've asked them
to leave the body
on site until your arrival.
And as of now,
all of our resources are
at your disposal.
You know, we still teach your
Belardo case at the academy.
Mm-hmm.
And you are?
Amelia Pembrock, I'm with
the Behavioral Science Unit.
I mean, uh, like,
what do you do?
Oh, I trace criminal profiles
based on forensic patterns.
HANK: Yeah.
I am also a field agent.
HANK:
Have you worked many cases?
No. This is my first.
[INDISTINCT RADIO CHATTER]
The river usually washes down
dead cattle, tree branches,
but this is not stuff
that we're used to seeing.
Ma'am, I gotta warn you that
what you're about
to see cannot be unseen.
I'll manage.
[BACKGROUND RADIO CHATTER]
[TRAIN HORN BLARES]
ALAN: Any suspects?
HANK: Nobody yet.
Then we found a witness
who saw a man dump a body.
He didn't report it at first,
because he thought it was a dog.
Dog?
Hunters up in the delta,
you can only fire a rifle next
to a bloodhound so many times
before it goes deaf.
Then the deaf dog
is a worthless dog.
Tell me about the vehicle.
Abandoned up
on Highway 61, fake plates.
Couldn't pull any prints.
You can forget about CCTV.
It's broken.
I talked to maintenance,
and they've been waiting
on new electrical since March.
Perfect timing.
Or maybe he knew.
Who reported the body?
Fishermen.
They saw fish eating away
at something under the surface
of the water and--
That's when you found it.
That's when we found
the first missing twin.
Alan Kramer,
this is Colin Ripley.
He's our medical examiner.
How do you do?
ALAN: Hi.
HANK:
Usually first on the scene.
[SIGHS]
All right. Shall we?
Yes, sir.
[BIRDS CHIRPING]
COLIN [SIGHS]:
Gretta Otto.
Since the twins were identical,
blood sample was the quickest
way to an ID.
Body was underwater all night.
Probably the worst place
to dump her.
Whoever did this wanted
the current to take her away.
But it didn't.
You think it might be
intentional?
Intentional?
Water that dirty could
be corrosive,
wash away evidence.
You said you checked the river
for the other body?
HANK: We did, every inch of it.
Uh-huh.
Could be ransom.
Ransom criminals do target
the wealthy. But--
If there's wealth in this town,
it's definitely the Ottos.
But then why not contact
the family?
If he wanted us
to find the body,
he would've dumped it
on the family porch.
So not a ransom.
Why? Did you see a note?
Did the witness provide
a description?
We tried to do a composite,
but it was too far away,
it was too dark.
AMELIA:
Sure.
If the media asks,
leave that part out.
Tell 'em our witness
got a clear look at our guy.
A clear look?
ALAN: Clear look.
AMELIA:
That's right.
It could draw out the killer
if we suggest he was spotted
in the area.
MAN 1:
Coming back empty.
Preliminary clues.
What about 'em?
What makes you think
it's a homicide?
Rope marks.
Wrists, neck.
They were either taken off after
or washed away by the water,
but they were there.
We also found tissue
under the fingernails.
ALAN:
Flesh?
It's too early to say.
There's, uh, one other thing.
It's pretty strange to see.
[UNZIPS BAG]
[BUZZING]
COLIN:
Her teeth have been smashed.
Likely the fall.
Wasn't the fall.
Look at her nose and her chin.
No fractures or visible cuts.
Rough landing would've bruised
more than just her mouth.
Bridge was just a drop-off spot.
There was blood on the rail.
ALAN:
Blunt force trauma.
Yeah, I saw that.
COLIN:
All right then,
mugging gone wrong.
Backpack was empty,
all contents taken.
Takes her books
and her lunchbox,
but leaves that gold bracelet?
I-I don't think we can
consider robbery a motive.
Yeah,
so why stage it as one?
MAN 2:
We found something!
What is it?
Looks like a gun.
A gun?
I don't understand.
He takes the risk
to drop her here,
off the busiest bridge,
right under everyone's nose.
Yeah.
You can go ahead
and bring her up.
All right,
let's bring her up, slowly,
respectfully.
There's a missing girl
out there.
If she's alive, she's counting
on us to find her.
[BIRDS CHIRPING]
[♪♪♪]
LAB ASSISTANT:
Rope marks confirm it.
She died of asphyxiation.
[CLICKS TONGUE]
It was intimate, personal.
Tell 'em about the teeth.
You were right.
Trauma to the teeth
wasn't from the fall.
Regular patterns, shaped,
purposeful.
Meaning what?
Inflicted separately?
After the murder,
but before dumping the body.
What do you know
about forensic odontology?
[SCRIBBLING]
Call the town's dentist.
He'll have some answers for you.
The pieces of flesh?
Under her fingernails?
Yeah.
Not human.
Chicken.
Chicken?
Raw chicken.
After hours underwater?
Current will wash out
fibers that small.
Apparently not fast enough.
LAB ASSISTANT: One last thing.
There were traces of nitrate
on the victim's elbow.
Your killer could have some
gunpowder residue.
But no wounds consistent
with firearms.
And no bullets
found on the scene.
We don't know yet
how the gun they found fits
in all this.
ALAN:
Hm.
AMELIA: Hm.
What are you thinking?
Our man planned this carefully,
studied the path
of the river,
understands
the city's geography.
A local.
Maybe.
But then why throw a gun
at the crime scene?
Lifetime of cases,
you scrape for one perfect piece
of evidence, and now all
of a sudden we've got too much.
This is the opposite
of a perfect crime.
It's too easy.
[THUNDER RUMBLING]
[RAIN PATTERING]
ARTHUR:
You know what
frightens me the most?
That I'll forget the sound
of their voices.
Go home to your wife,
Arthur.
When my daughters went missing,
I went against
my lawyer's advice
and I came straight to you.
You wanna know why?
'Cause you're the best.
All those victims
you've rescued,
all of their stories are
now baked into your legacy.
Remember what you once told me,
"You are who you save."
[CLICKS TONGUE]
I understand how difficult it is
trusting others
with your daughters' life.
But can a marriage survive
the death of a child,
let alone two?
She's alive.
Try to have faith, Arthur.
I just don't know how.
Those people that I sent,
they're trained for this.
They'll piece together
the clues, solve the case,
and find her.
I know they'll find her.
I just don't know
if it'll be quick enough.
Go to Canton.
Your team needs you.
[BIRDS CHIRPING]
[CAR DOORS OPEN AND CLOSE]
Once inside, I have
to show her some photos.
Photos of what?
The girl's body?
Some things only a mother
would know.
Are we sure it's the best time?
Why,
you know a better time?
20 minutes max.
ILSA:
My husband said
you'd be coming.
What do you remember about
the hours leading up
to the disappearance?
ILSA:
It was a day like any other.
They left school,
and they were supposed
to come right home.
ALAN: But they didn't.
Mm.
Took me hours to realize
that something was wrong.
Did they always walk back?
ILSA:
Sometimes.
It's really far.
Yeah, but they did everything
together,
one always keeping an eye out
for the other.
AMELIA:
So you never felt
it was dangerous?
No. Things like this might be
common in big cities, but here,
crime is nonexistent.
Was their last name
ever a problem?
No. Why?
Are you thinking this
is some kind of ransom?
Mrs. Otto.
Ilsa.
We think a case of this nature
is of personal matter.
Do you know anybody that would
have a grudge against
your husband or an interest
in your daughters?
No.
ALAN: No.
Everybody knew them.
They're sweet girls,
and they're so polite,
and they're very
hardworking, too.
What type of work?
Community jobs,
after school activities.
They worked at the medical lab
and the butcher shop.
For their age, that's a little--
It's-It's unusual.
Yeah, I know.
It's just Arthur
really encouraged the girls
to get involved.
I-It's not easy, you know,
for a child to grow up
and feel normal when all they've
ever known is wealth.
My daughter experienced
more pain
in a single night than I have
in my entire life,
and she was a--
a good girl, Detective.
She was so good.
What does a 14-year-old
have to do
to deserve something like this?
She died face down in a river.
She was alone,
and she was just waiting
on somebody from home
to come get her.
[CRIES]
Look,
I had to sign
the death certificate
on my own child today.
My other daughter
is still out there.
She's missing, and you're here.
I know
what you're going through.
Do you?
Do you have children?
[DOOR OPENS]
[HEELS CLACKING]
[DOOR CLOSES]
Did you get everything
you need?
Yeah, enough to get started.
Captain Graysmith
has great admiration
for your history,
says you are
a fine investigator.
And for that reason,
my wife and I,
we will follow your decisions,
whatever it takes,
just so long as you bring
our daughter back.
Yes, sir.
We'll do our best.
[FOOTSTEPS RECEDING]
AMELIA:
I know Canton somehow
doesn't have a digital archive,
but are you sure the library
is the best place to start?
[PEN CLICKING]
It's quiet.
I'm just surprised you
of all people don't want us out
in the field.
They're scouting
all the bridges,
following the currents
from sunrise to sundown.
They're not gonna miss
another body.
What's this?
It's old articles,
criminal history of the city.
Barely has any.
You looking for clues?
Connections
to previous murders.
What makes you think
there are any?
AMELIA:
I don't,
but if we're looking
for patterns,
this is where we'd find 'em.
Ah.
Okay, let's--
Let's say she's still alive.
Why kidnap two girls
and only murder one?
Brewster said
Gretta was the bigger twin,
so maybe he got rid
of one sister to get
to the other.
Gotta stop saying he.
We don't know
the suspect is male.
Yeah, that's our killer,
a 95-pound female with a kink
for little girls
who's fit enough
to single-handedly lift a body
up and over a railing.
All right,
you made your point.
All right.
I strangle you,
I tie you up,
and I load you into
the back of a vehicle.
Without leaving
any fingerprints.
ALAN:
But why do I drop you off here
where anybody could see me?
Because you're a moron.
But I'm not a moron.
I didn't leave a single
fingerprint.
Okay.
So you smash my teeth
at the last moment,
dump my body.
ALAN: Mm.
If it's not for torture--
It's out of precaution.
But why?
You need to ask
a professional.
ODONTOLOGIST [OVER PHONE]:
Children's mouths
evolve quickly, drastically.
I know this is crucial
to the investigation,
but I fear reconstructing
a mold of her mouth
will prove difficult.
How difficult?
ODONTOLOGIST:
Every set of teeth
is one of a kind,
like a fingerprint.
Reconstruction can be done?
FORENSIC ODONTOLOGIST:
With patience, yes.
Working off past records
could take days.
All right.
Call me when you have something.
GRAYSMITH:
Wasn't easy
to secure this meeting.
AMELIA [OVER PHONE]:
Think we can trust him?
Guy's a fox.
Best reporter in town.
GRAYSMITH [OVER PHONE]:
Trade information carefully.
Ma'am?
Yes?
AMELIA [OVER PHONE]:
Thank you for the opportunity.
Work as a team, Pembrock.
Don't take shortcuts.
Close this case,
no matter the cost.
[PHONE BEEPS]
[BIRDS CAWING]
Since yesterday, police
and press have received
hundreds of tips.
ALAN:
Let me guess.
All anonymous.
Phones won't stop ringing.
Everybody wants to report
on rivals, neighbors,
even family members,
anybody with strange
sexual habits.
Some are calling claiming they
committed the murder themselves.
You know they're not guilty.
That's right.
Nobody can provide us
with new information.
Everything they say
is public already.
You think the killer's
in it for the press?
He could be tracking
the investigation
from the inside, yeah.
AMELIA:
Making sure
it doesn't get too close to him.
Mm-hmm.
So all we need is a name.
I don't work the crime desk.
Can you get us
to somebody that does?
Yeah, sure.
Ask for Julie Trembley.
T-R-E-M-B-L-E-Y.
Let's talk about the bridge.
What about the bridge?
[CHUCKLES]
Come on. He coulda
dropped the body anywhere,
but he chose the busiest area.
Why?
That's not cleanup.
That's a message.
You're right.
Zodiac,
Monster of Florence.
Killers typically dump bodies
outside the city, a field--
Or a park.
Somewhere they'll go
unnoticed.
So he wanted us to find her?
The body getting stuck
in the rocks wasn't an accident.
It was a choice.
They did find a .357
at the riverside.
Victim have any wounds
consistent with a gun?
Oh, oh, where you going?
Library.
Hey.
Excuse me.
Hey!
[FLIPPING PAGES]
This stuck with me.
I just couldn't see
the connection until now.
ALAN:
What are you talking about?
"Remains of a unknown male,
found after a structure fire."
So?
High-heat fire.
No prints,
no way to ID the body.
One distinguishing factor.
Teeth.
Like a fingerprint.
Oh.
What if it wasn't
torture or a fetish?
What if he actually thought
we couldn't ID the body?
But we did.
We saw the face,
her-her-her dress.
A mother could identify
the body.
What if-- What if he
expected more decomp?
He thought fish would eat away
at her features.
That's-that's why he attracted
them with the fiber.
Fibers?
Under the fingernails.
The--
ALAN: Raw chicken. Okay.
Who-who-who deals
with-with raw chicken
on a daily basis?
Cook.
Farmer.
Butcher.
[ALAN SIGHS]
[KNOCKING AT DOOR]
Gleen.
Is it locked?
Says 9:00 a.m.
[DOOR BELL JINGLES]
AMELIA:
Mr. Gleen.
Sheriff's department.
[BIRDS CHIRPING]
AMELIA:
You open?
[DOORS OPEN]
Can I help you?
[RAIN PATTERING]
It's almost midnight.
We need to get started
before he realizes
he can call a lawyer.
[DOOR OPENS]
The results are negative.
On what?
Gunpowder residue?
On everything.
Fingers, hands, elbows.
No match.
Shit.
ALAN:
You all right?
You got a headache?
Mm.
The worst kind.
So who's going in first?
Can't take turns.
If that's our guy,
we gotta crack him
on the first try.
Crack him?
It's been two days.
We have too many leads,
no real suspects.
Time is running out.
We can't go in empty-handed.
The butcher, where's his file?
What file?
Uh, all right.
Here we go.
Congratulations, you--
you just earned years' worth
of evidence on your suspect,
enough to drag him to court.
Let's crank the heat,
turn that room into a furnace.
Nothing makes them talk faster.
Have we considered
the possibility of a polygraph?
HANK:
We do have a lie detector.
ALAN:
If we can catch the killer,
we find the missing girl.
Okay. So we don't let him
leave until he takes the test.
[CASE CLOSES]
Whoa, whoa, whoa, whoa.
We? Where do you think
you're going?
In there with you.
No, you're not.
I'm going in there alone.
This guy has a history
of harassing girls.
We need someone
with my perspective.
And what perspective
would that be?
That of a woman.
[BEEPS]
ALAN:
Thank you for waiting.
Now, these are just
preliminary questions
we're asking anybody that
we think can help with the case.
Okay.
Before we get started,
can I get you anything?
You want a coffee
or a cigarette, perhaps?
We're new here.
What about you?
Live here long?
BORIS:
I'm born and raised.
You certainly know
your way around town.
Local butcher.
Everyone seems to trust you.
I guess.
ALAN: Hm.
Known the Otto girls long?
Uh, a couple years.
Um, Annie used to come in weekly
to pick up meat for her family.
AMELIA:
Mm.
Is that why you gave her
a summer job?
Felt like you knew 'em?
She seemed eager to work
and looked friendly,
learned quickly.
How long you been a butcher?
30 years this summer.
Wow, that's a long time.
I bet the sight of blood
doesn't trigger you anymore.
How-how old were you
when you started, you know,
killing livestock?
Five, six.
Trained at the shop.
AMELIA: Family business?
BORIS: Yeah.
You own a gun, Mr. Gleen?
BORIS:
I kept one at the house.
Is that a requirement
for the job?
No, more a passion
for hunting.
[TAKES A DRAG]
ALAN:
Fox?
No, deer.
Deer.
And since when has that
been illegal?
Your gun.
Anything like this?
BORIS:
Smith & Wesson.
That's the most popular gun
in America, sir.
So what?
Strange choice
for hunting, though.
Well, no, um, it's mostly
for target practice.
ALAN:
So it is your gun?
No, mine was stolen.
ALAN: Stolen?
[TAKES A DRAG]
I filed a report right away.
Right.
You mean this.
Complaint of theft.
So let me get this straight.
Someone breaks into your house,
all they steal is a gun.
Seems kinda odd.
Well, I'm telling the truth.
Can you turn the heat down
in here? God.
Do you know the gun was found
at the crime scene, Mr. Gleen?
[BORIS COUGHS]
You guys, you guys--
[COUGHS]
Have me confused
with somebody else.
What about your shop?
It says here you had complaints
filed against you.
Girls.
Why do you have
so much information on me?
Since when is that illegal?
Oh, wait.
You think I'm the killer.
The day they went missing,
the girls were seen
leaving their school.
Told friends they were going
straight home.
Now, you claim it's been months
since they were at your shop.
Yeah, it's true.
ALAN:
So how is it we found traces
of raw chicken
under her fingernails?
Same chicken
on your hands right now.
Yeah, I'm not--
I'm not answering
any more of your questions,
'cause I never
touched those girls.
You have me confused
with somebody else,
so unless you have a real reason
to keep me here,
I gotta get home
and tend to my mama.
Thank you very much, Mr. Gleen.
[♪♪♪]
[DOOR OPENS, SHUTS]
[TRAIN PASSING]
AMELIA:
I'm telling you,
he's our guy.
GRAYSMITH:
Now, how can you be sure?
He's what they call
a "methodical killer."
He's emotionally scarred,
shows signs
of psychosexual
motivation.
Come on, what signs?
HANK: Slow down.
He practices on animals
before he attempts a kill.
He fits the profile perfectly.
We're basing this
on a theory?
There's a difference
between killing chickens
and murdering children.
Sexually dysfunctional males
develop a hatred
when they lack contact
with women their age.
What are you saying?
I'm saying
people get lonely.
GRAYSMITH:
There were no traces
of sexual assault.
Some achieve fulfillment
from the act of violence alone.
Why?
He hates women
because he wants them.
GRAYSMITH:
But he can't bring
himself to have them.
Which is why the body
doesn't show traces of rape.
ALAN:
We need to focus less
on pre-crime behavior
and more on post-crime
investigation.
Meaning?
Meaning less theory,
more proof.
Just because you think
somebody's a killer doesn't mean
they are one.
Had you not let him go,
he'd still be hooked up
to a lie detector
giving us answers.
[INHALES] You know what--
[KNOCKING ON DOOR]
Ah, the Otto files?
Bring that in here.
You-- you read the files.
The guy has a history
of sexual harassment.
Let's talk
to his former employees,
they're all women,
and get one of them to testify.
ALAN:
He's not our guy, Pembrock.
Looks nothing
like the identikit.
You said it was too dark to see.
200 pounds, 6 foot.
A guy like that's hard to miss.
Brewster.
Yeah.
It's a small town,
but it's not that small.
You saw his hands.
He could crush your face
with one blow,
and he understands anatomy
for a living.
You have to be strong
to pull something off like this,
I give you that,
but this man is sick.
He has diabetes.
I'm sorry.
Why are we focusing all
of our energy on one guy?
That's what I've been saying.
Because now that
he knows he's a suspect,
he'll destroy any remaining
evidence.
Did you search the shop?
HANK: Not yet.
There was hair on the floor.
Tell me we sampled it.
With what warrant?
Real-life applications
require real-life experience.
[SLAMS BOOK]
You can't always
judge a book by its cover,
'cause sooner or later,
it'll bite you in the ass.
[FOOTSTEPS RECEDING]
[FOOTSTEPS APPROACHING]
[FIRE BLAZING IN DISTANCE]
I'm so sorry I'm late.
[PANTING]
[PULLS OFF TAPE]
[PANTS]
[FLIPPING PAGES]
[INDISTINCT RADIO CHATTER]
[POLICE SIREN WAILING]
[♪♪♪]
[FLICKS PAGES]
[ELEVATOR BELL DINGS]
Hi.
Sorry.
Hey.
Uh, is there a duplicate?
In the archives, you mean?
Yeah.
Nope. This is it.
It's just that the checkout
list is incomplete.
Oh, dear.
Wonder what happened.
Why would anyone
not want their name on here?
[TAPS FINGER]
[TRAFFIC PASSING]
[ALAN CHUCKLES]
Better at this than I was
when I was your age.
Uh, I play during homeroom.
[CHESS PIECE THUDS]
ALAN:
You ever play her?
Once.
I don't think
she liked me.
Your teachers say you
liked her.
It's okay to have a crush.
[CHUCKLES]
I'm trying
to bring her sister home.
You think you could help me?
You recognize that?
Yeah.
Their mom said that she
didn't buy it for them.
ALAN:
Gretta tell you
where she got it from?
Was it a gift?
It was?
From someone older?
Was it a friend?
Maybe a secret friend?
Do they teach chess
in police school?
You know, they should.
Learned more on this board
than I did out in the field.
Isn't being a detective harder?
Not really.
Both about the big picture.
Predicting moves,
anticipating outcomes.
[CHESS PIECE THUDS]
LUKE: Check.
It's okay.
You can still win.
HANK:
The Ottos are holding
a wake for their daughter.
They're hoping
to raise awareness
and remind people that
Anna's still missing.
Where's Pembrock?
Assumed she'd be with you.
[CARS PASSING BY]
[♪♪♪]
Ms. Trembley?
Amelia Pembrock.
Mike Bowers said you'd be
willing to talk about the case.
Great.
I was wondering
if I could buy you dinner.
[CAR PASSING]
[BIRDS CHIRPING]
So how long did you work
at the butcher shop?
Less than a year.
I quit when things got
uncomfortable.
He make passes at you?
JULIE:
Flirting I'm used to.
He was more interested
in proximity than contact,
physical, that is.
First, he asked me
to stay late nights,
just watch me handle meat
from across the room,
then the stalking began.
Followed me home, got creepy.
But he never touched you?
Trust me, wouldn't let him.
Asked him to stop.
One night, I punched him.
Holy shit.
That-that only made
things worse.
The more aggressive I got,
the more he was into it.
Worst part is,
he never lost his cool.
So then what happened?
I quit, moved across town.
Started working at the paper.
Crime desk was always
my calling.
You guys arrest people
with a warrant.
All I need is to get 'em
on the front page.
Did you ever see him again?
JULIE:
He moved on
to his next employee.
He prefers them young, you see.
Hmm.
But to be honest,
I know the guy.
He's not who you're looking for.
What makes you say that?
I spoke to Brewster,
saw the photos.
I know what you think he did,
but the Butcher,
he's not built for this.
He's too shy.
Too shy?
Too sloppy.
Off the record,
I think there's a reason
you're bathing in evidence.
AMELIA:
Uh-huh.
You guys found a .357
at the crime scene, right?
And nobody found it
suspiciously easy?
Four cases out of five,
murder weapon is never found,
and you guys fish one out the
same morning less than 50 yards
away from the body.
How do you know all of this?
I'd suck at my job
if I didn't have sources.
When a crime this big
unfolds in a town this small,
you can't expect people
to just stay put.
Listen--
[SIGHS]
I'm happy to help,
but if you want me
to share my homework,
then you better do the same.
[CAR PASSES]
[TRAIN HORN BLARING IN DISTANCE]
People dump stuff off the bridge
all the time, coins, garbage.
So yeah--
Mm-hmm.
You could assume the gun
was dumped on a different day
by a different person
for a different reason,
but look closely.
Not a trace of rust.
Half the serial number's
still legible.
Which is how they pulled a clean
sample of the nitrate powder.
Clues like these disappear
in a matter of hours.
Somehow, this one didn't.
How does everyone around here
know so much about guns?
[CHUCKLES]
If you wanna speculate,
whoever it is,
he's been carefully planting
evidence to throw you off.
You're looking
in all the wrong places.
This article you found.
Mm-hmm.
You said Gretta's teeth
were smashed,
her bite one of a kind.
So?
So what if they didn't smash
them to cover up her identity?
What if what they wanted to hide
was something else entirely?
Like a mark?
A bite mark.
Brookfield, June '94,
victim bites into the foot
of her aggressor.
Takes them years to notice
one of their suspects
is hiding a scar, an exact match
to the victim's teeth.
No teeth, no print.
You'd have nothing
to ID it by.
And all this evidence,
where'd you get it?
Where did you get it?
[LAUGHS]
Okay.
So let's say the butcher
was bitten.
JULIE:
Uh, can I say something?
Move on from the obvious.
For years,
I let him call me names,
haunt my social life.
Nobody wants to see him punished
more than I do,
but you're losing yourself
in a rabbit hole.
Stop mistaking coincidence
for proof.
First guy we interview,
and within hours,
he cleans out his shop
and his home.
I'm sure you're right,
no coincidence there.
Thank you
for all your time.
Appreciate it.
[THUNDER RUMBLING]
[FOOTSTEPS APPROACHING]
Black looks good on you.
You said
it's a wake, right?
A memorial,
family organized.
We say a few words then.
Alan.
Hmm.
It's been three days
since these girls disappeared,
and I really appreciate you
coming here and working hard
on this case.
But you and I both know it,
if we don't find this girl
in the next 24 hours,
statistically speaking,
chances are she won't be back
at all.
Hmm.
You think the killer
will be there tonight,
out in the crowd?
[CROWS CAWING]
GRAYSMITH:
Tonight's about
a community uniting,
about the bigger plan
God has for us all.
Who loses their husband
is known as a widow.
Who loses their parents
is known as an orphan.
But if you lose a kid--
[SIGHS]
You don't even get a name
to be defined by.
Whose idea was it
to organize this memorial?
Mother? Father?
GRAYSMITH:
Should have to bury their child.
Neither. It was Pembrock's
suggestion.
Amelia. Why?
Because it wouldn't be uncommon
for him to take part,
participate in these kinds of--
Yes, community meetings.
You think he'd risk
exposing himself?
It's the next best thing
to going back
to the crime scene,
relive the experience,
some more of that euphoria.
We will find Anna.
We will bring her home.
These girls mean so much
to this community.
I understand the pain
of the parents,
'cause I myself would do
anything to protect my family.
And with God as my witness
I will not stop
until we bring our child home.
Where are the suspects?
We ask that you respect
the privacy of the family--
You were supposed
to protect them.
Give us names!
If you or anyone has information
that can help us find her--
Is Anna dead?
You're protecting the killer.
Say it!
[CROWD SHOUTING]
Wait, wait, wait, wait, wait.
MAN 3: Is Anna dead?
St-- stop.
All right, back, back, back,
back, back, back, back, go, go.
Take her!
Get her!
Mrs. Otto, I--
[SLAPS]
[CROWD GASPS]
I just found out the police
had a suspect in custody,
and you let them go.
When our daughters went missing,
we trusted you for your help.
To lead the investigation,
we allowed you
to follow dead ends off
the promise that you would be
delivering justice.
Mr. Otto--
But now my daughter's future
could end up being
yesterday's headlines.
And we will not find peace
until our Anna is brought back.
Now,
whether Anna's alive
or in a body bag
is entirely up to you.
Come on. Let's go.
[ILSA SNIFFLES]
[INDISTINCT CHATTER]
[SIGHS]
This is getting out of hand.
The city's turning on us.
They want an outcome.
They want closure.
Well, unsolved murders is
bad press for anyone involved.
We're running out
of options.
Sometimes any suspect
is better than no suspect.
How can a case this
simple be so difficult to solve?
Maybe it's not as simple
as we think.
We've gotta be missing
something.
Okay,
the Otto girls leave school here
and they're meant
to arrive home here.
But they never do.
Which means somewhere
along this path our suspect
approaches them.
Someone they're
familiar with,
not out of the ordinary.
AMELIA:
They trust him.
Maybe he offered 'em
a ride home,
gave 'em false information,
tricked them into following him.
How do we know it was
a planned homicide
and not a kidnapping?
We don't.
Maybe all he wanted
to do was play.
GRAYSMITH:
Hmm?
In the hopes to let 'em go,
promise
to make it his little game.
He gets pleasure
from the proximity alone.
Game?
What kind of game?
AMELIA:
Could be anyone's guess.
Soft choking,
dominating the victim.
ALAN:
So he ties 'em up.
It's all part of the agreement.
Except they panic,
things get out of hand
real quick,
and the game turns into a fight.
A fight into murder.
So Gretta tries
to defend herself.
She fights back.
She bites him.
That wound is now
a one-of-a-kind fingerprint.
So he smashes the teeth--
AMELIA: Mm-hmm.
So it won't come back to him.
When it comes time
to ditch the body,
he chooses a place where it's
likely to get stuck underwater.
Trying to wash away
all the evidence.
ALAN:
But he doesn't consider
the tide.
The body surfaces too soon.
We find it.
After he kills the first twin,
he doesn't let the other one go.
GRAYSMITH:
Why?
Well,
he can't just drop her off.
She'll talk.
ALAN:
Right.
So he detains her.
He's hoping to keep playing.
Same game, different outcome.
All right.
Let's just say this
is what happens.
All right?
Now the question is who.
AMELIA:
I went back to the library,
found a ledger
on child abduction.
The checkout list was ripped.
One name was missing.
GRAYSMITH:
Who wouldn't want a record
of ever checking out
that binder?
I know who.
The Otto girls left
for school here.
The butcher lives
with his mother here.
Curb to curb, it's a block.
He watched them out his window
for months before finally doing
something about it.
Did you know about that?
He didn't take them
to his shop.
He took them
to his home.
Ah, it's a great theory.
Still doesn't explain the gun.
He's right.
No bullets fired,
no shells recovered,
so how does that factor in?
Maybe it doesn't.
Maybe it never did.
We have to get a warrant
to search the butcher's home.
Now, how am I gonna get
the prosecutor
to give us a warrant when we
barely have any evidence?
Every day that goes by,
it gets more and more difficult
to collect any.
We're trying.
AMELIA:
Aren't you sick of trying?
Stop.
AMELIA: It's either this
or we just wait
for the other body to wash up.
We know!
Do you really think
this is a coincidence?
[BANGS TABLE]
Enough!
Look, you came here to assist
and observe.
But so far all I've seen
from you is guesses
and theories.
You've been absent
for days assembling a case
of your own.
What are you really
trying to say?
You're good
at figuring people out.
Why don't you tell me?
You want honesty?
You're lost.
A caricature
of your former self,
desperate to retire
in spite of your age.
You reek of alcohol
every day that we're out here.
At this point,
you're really only as good as
your opinions,
which you're reticent to offer,
because you have none.
The only good part of your day
is the few seconds
after you wake up,
before you remember
that you're waking up
to a world that he's not in.
ALAN:
Go home, Amelia.
Get some sleep.
[FOOTSTEPS RECEDING]
GRAYSMITH:
Amelia.
Maybe you're onto something,
but without enough evidence,
even the best of us
couldn't draw a connection.
You think he really did it?
Prove it.
[THUNDER RUMBLING]
[FOOTSTEPS RECEDING]
[♪♪♪]
[DOG BARKING]
[CLICKS LIGHTER]
[CAR SCREECHING IN DISTANCE]
[DOG BARKING]
[POLICE SIREN WAILING]
[♪♪♪]
[WINDOW SLIDES OPEN]
[DOOR CREAKS OPEN]
[HISSING FROM TANK]
[PLASTIC RUSTLES]
[FLY BUZZING]
[GRUNTS]
[CLANKING OPEN, CLOSES]
[CLANKS CLOSED]
[DRAWER THUDS]
[DOOR CLOSES]
[EXHALES]
[KEYS JANGLE]
[GASPS]
Mama?
[MOTHER WHIMPERS]
Mama.
[MOTHER WHIMPERING]
[THUDS]
[PANTING]
[UNZIPS BAG]
[PLASTIC RUSTLES]
[SIGHS]
Oh God.
[WINDOW CREAKS CLOSED]
[THUDS]
[PANTING]
[FOOTSTEPS APPROACHING]
[INDISTINCT CHATTER]
GRAYSMITH:
Just in time.
That's the prosecutor's office.
We can have a warrant
as early as today.
What's this?
GRAYSMITH:
New evidence.
Matches the girl's shoes.
Where'd you get it?
They didn't say.
Came in middle of the night,
anonymous drop-off.
More importantly, the DNA
on it matches the butcher.
When we found the girl,
Gretta was wearing both shoes.
Did the family call in
a missing shoe?
No.
Is her DNA on the shoe?
GRAYSMITH:
Technically, no.
The size and color are a match.
This proves nothing.
We can't go around
arresting people
for their shopping habits.
AMELIA:
The butcher doesn't
have kids, no nieces either.
What is a grown man doing buying
children's shoes?
This isn't proof.
ALAN:
You've got to be pretty
desperate to call this evidence.
Well, we are desperate.
Guilty or not, you can't
take back a murder charge.
People will start talking.
We certainly wouldn't
want them to come
to the wrong conclusion,
would we?
You're making a mistake.
GRAYSMITH:
Look, if we want a warrant,
I need to make a call
in the next five minutes
or we have to wait till Monday.
Where are you going?
I'm going to eat,
to sleep,
maybe relax
a little bit.
You know,
you should do the same.
You're not good
to anybody being up all night.
Kramer--
And uh,
Ripley's on duty
downstairs.
You can get that wound
looked at.
[TRAIN PASSING IN BACKGROUND]
[SNIPS]
Done.
Guess that glass of wine
in the bath
wasn't such a great idea.
[CHUCKLES]
Wine glass, huh?
'Cause judging by that cut
I just stitched up,
I'd say you were drinking out
of a 5-foot metal vase.
[PEN CLICKS]
You'll report it?
I have to.
Lab stocks up on my supplies.
They're gonna need
to know what I used it for.
Why?
What do you think
I should write?
A minor domestic accident.
Whatever it takes
to keep you out in the field.
Now, get out there
and catch that son of a bitch.
AMELIA:
Thank you.
[CAR PASSES BY]
[♪♪♪]
A whiskey, double.
Please.
[BACKGROUND CHATTER, LAUGHTER]
[FOOTSTEPS APPROACHING]
I should thank you.
With a single accusation,
you managed to shake
my life up with ruthless
efficiency.
First, you put my name
in the papers.
Then within a couple days, all
my customers just disappeared.
That's when the death threats
started.
[LAUGHTER IN BACKGROUND]
I had to close the shop.
Five generations of work, gone.
[CHEERING AND CLAPPING
IN BACKGROUND]
God only knows how I'm gonna
care for mama.
But-- but--
[SIGHS]
But at least we know
how one man's
opinion can thoroughly destroy
the life of a complete stranger.
But that day you came to see me,
I guess you didn't
consider that, did you?
[COUGHS]
[SNIFFLES]
[SIPS, GULPS]
You know detective,
I have nothing to hide from you.
[LAUGHS]
But-- [SNIFFLES]
But even if I did,
what makes you think
I'd ever tell you?
[GULPS]
[SIGHS]
[POLICE SIREN WAILING]
[TIRES SCREECHING]
WOMAN 2:
What's going on?
[WHISTLE BLOWING]
[DOOR OPENS, BELL JINGLES]
Amelia, it's over.
The butcher is-- is dead.
[PANTS]
We all knew this case would
reach a satisfying conclusion.
Earlier today,
Boris Gleen took his own life.
Though the confession
wasn't secured in time,
we have reason
to believe he was the man
who kidnapped
and murdered Gretta Otto.
So what was his motive?
Well, we have yet to--
Is it true that
one of the investigators
was seen drinking
with the suspect?
Wha-- uh,
I'm not sure about that.
What about Anna Otto?
REPORTER:
Have they found a body?
No, we have not yet
found a body. But we are--
[CROWD CLAMORING]
Please, the investigation
will continue as planned.
Justice for Gretta
has been made!
[CROWD SHOUTING]
ALAN:
Congratulations.
That's a hell of a first case.
Must be happy.
Methodical theory,
predictable outcome,
everything by the books.
That's what you wanted,
right?
[SCOFFS]
I'm packing my bags,
leaving tomorrow,
first flight out.
You should probably do the same.
[THUNDER RUMBLING]
They still teach forensic
mythology at the academy?
Mm-hmm.
My first week,
they gathered all the cadets
this big auditorium,
wanted to speak to us
about good and evil.
Saint Gabriel and the dragon,
you know that story?
No.
[CLICKS TONGUE]
There was this knight
named Gabriel.
They said he was a saint,
but really he was just
a good man.
Sword, code of honor.
And one day this dragon shows up
and so he travels
to the mountains to fight it.
But it's not the type
of dragon you see
in fairy tales,
it's something much worse.
Doesn't just breathe fire,
it-- it whispers lies,
it stirs fear.
It turns people on each other,
eats them from within.
So days go by and then weeks,
and everybody's waiting
for Gabriel to come back, but
never does.
After all these years
in the academy,
that's the first thing you hear,
but it's the hardest thing
to learn,
is that sometimes
the dragon wins.
I just wanted
to catch him alive,
you know?
Retirement won't bring him back.
I know it was never about that.
You just want the feeling
to go away.
You want closure.
[THUNDER RUMBLES]
[DOOR CREAKS OPEN]
ALAN:
Hello?
Hey.
COLIN:
Building's empty.
Didn't think I'd find you here.
Come to say goodbye?
Yeah, I'm
on the first flight out.
I wanted to say thank you
for everything.
You tried your best.
We all did.
Yeah.
I don't know, maybe this is
all my fault.
What's that?
It's a mold
of the girl's teeth.
Finally came in.
Who knew reconstruction
could take this long?
I doubt it would've made
a difference.
Want me
to get it off your hands?
You checked the butcher's
body, right?
Yeah.
For bite marks?
I could add it
to the inventory
with the rest of the evidence.
Let me take it.
No, I-I can handle it.
COLIN:
All right.
Yeah.
Thanks, man.
Yeah, man.
Thank you.
So what now?
Talks of locking down the city.
Roadblocks at every access.
Nobody gets in or out
until a second body shows up.
Maybe I should stay.
Oh no, you should leave.
Doesn't take a doctor
to notice that this case has
been devouring you
from the inside like a cancer
getting worse by the minute.
I wouldn't forgive myself
if it pushed you
to the breaking point.
Checking out another book?
Just returning this please.
Okay.
Did you find what you were
looking for?
Uh, almost.
All right. Well, if you
would please just sign
the log here, first name
and initials.
Oh, forgot.
The log's damaged.
Oh, I will get a new one.
[FOOTSTEPS RECEDING]
[SIGHS]
[SHADING]
Hey, miss. I--
Miss, wait.
It's ironic, isn't it?
What's that?
All this evidence,
yet this bracelet still remains
the biggest mystery.
You seem fixed on it.
[RUBBER GLOVES SNAPPING OFF]
You know, I'm done here.
I could--
I could walk you out
if you want, okay?
Just give me a minute.
[WATER RUNNING]
You ashamed of your scars,
doctor?
Oh, yeah.
My wife finds it hideous.
Looks like it hurts.
Well, they always get
infected this time of year.
I didn't know healed scars
were prone to reinfection.
[CHUCKLES]
[LINE RINGING, BEEPS]
Kramer, I was wrong.
It was never the butcher.
I know who the killer is.
I'll tell you what,
first thing Monday,
I'll go through
the inventory again,
and I'll see if anyone
has anything more
on that bracelet gift to Gretta.
What-what-what shape
was that again?
It's a horseshoe shape.
But I never told you
it was a gift.
[DOOR CREAKS OPEN]
You're the last ones out.
See you Monday.
[DOOR SHUTS]
When I first met them,
they were in need
of a father figure.
What else was I supposed to do?
I swear they were having
just as much fun as I was.
This was meant to be a game.
It was our little secret.
Shame one of them
had to spoil everything.
[GUN CLICKS]
[GUNSHOT]
[GRUNTS]
[EXHALES]
[GUN FALLS]
[CLATTERING]
[LID OPENS]
[HISSING FROM TANK]
MAN 7:
Dr. Ripley?
[DOOR CREAKS OPEN]
[POLICE SIREN WAILING]
[TRUNK CLOSES]
[KEYS JANGLE]
[♪♪♪]
[PANTS]
[SEAT BELT CLICKS]
ID, please.
Uh, yes. Uh, officer,
I'm uh, transporting medicine.
It's-- it's urgent.
Uh, one moment.
Please shut off the car.
Okay.
[INDISTINCT RADIO CHATTER]
[PANTS]
[MIRROR CREAKS]
Shit.
[THUMPING]
[SEAT BELT UNBUCKLES]
[PANTING, GROANING]
OFFICER 1:
Sir, I need you
to get back in your vehicle.
Back in your car.
[GROANS]
Sir, get back
in your car, please.
Are you okay?
Are you all right?
Give me an EMT up right away.
Give me an EMT up--
[GRUNTS]
What?
[GUNSHOT]
[WOMAN SCREAMING]
[THUDS]
[PANTING]
[GASPS]
[HEAVY BREATHING]
WOMAN 3: Oh my God!
[INDISTINCT SPEECH]
[PANTING]
[SIRENS WAILING]
[GUNSHOTS]
[GASPS]
Stand down!
Don't shoot!
[POLICE SIREN WAILING]
[TIRES SCREECHING]
OFFICER 2:
Get to cover. Get back.
OFFICER 3:
Get your hands...
[TIRES SCREECHING]
[PEOPLE SCREAMING]
[PANTS]
I never meant to plant evidence
or for anyone to get hurt.
I don't care why you did it.
Just give up.
I can help you survive this.
[KEYS JANGLE]
[GUNSHOT]
[PEOPLE SCREAM]
[GUNSHOTS]
WOMAN 4: Oh my God!
[BACKGROUND CHATTER]
OFFICER 4:
Suspect is down.
[INDISTINCT SPEECH]
Clear the area.
OFFICER 5: Officer down.
You're safe.
Can I take it?
Are you hurt?
[TRAIN MOVING]
[FOOTSTEPS APPROACHING]
ANNOUNCER [OVER PA]:
Attention all passengers,
train departing
from platform one will be
leaving in 10 minutes.
Didn't I warn you
that a town like this will
surprise you
in all the worst ways?
[SIGHS]
In case like this,
you learn more
in a week than you would have
with years of training.
Right. Yeah.
The Otto family is in lifelong
gratitude to you, as am I.
Wish I could have done more.
It's from the town.
They don't want you
to forget about them.
Even if I wanted to.
It's gonna be strange
taking over his office.
He would have wanted you to.
I heard about your dissertation.
Your students, they'll be lucky
to have you at the academy.
I was hoping to stay
in the field, actually.
What do you think,
Captain?
Oh, it's Major now.
Mm-hmm.
Got any new cases,
Major?
Ah, what do you know
about hostage negotiation?
There's always a first time.
[LAUGHS]
New York?
Well,
your bag's already packed.
Take your time.
Think it over.
No need.
Tell them
I'm on my way.
[♪♪♪]